<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Theory | Matt Kustra</title>
    <link>https://kustra-matt.github.io/tag/theory/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://kustra-matt.github.io/tag/theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Theory</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://kustra-matt.github.io/media/icon_hu968023516251523fc9a78b9c44e7eeb6_483323_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Theory</title>
      <link>https://kustra-matt.github.io/tag/theory/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alternative reproductive tactics</title>
      <link>https://kustra-matt.github.io/project/art/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kustra-matt.github.io/project/art/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am interested in the evolution and maintenance of alternative reproductive tactics. My main study system for my PhD was the unique and intriguing ocellated wrasse (&lt;em&gt;Symphodus ocellatus&lt;/em&gt;)! In this species there are three distinct male morphs: (1) nesting males, (2) satellite males, and (3) sneaker males. Females have a strong preference for nesting males who provide all the parental care. Sneaker males will try to sneak in during matings. Satellite males help nesting males chase away sneakers, but when given the opportunity will also try to sneak spawns. During my dissertation, I investigated how sneakers and satellite males differ in sneaking delays and how the social environment influence sneaking delays. We found that satellites have shorter sneak-spawning delays than sneakers, a benefit of their cooperation with nesting males. Sneak-spawning delays decreased with increasing nest activity for sneakers but not for satellites, suggesting that sneakers may, counter intuitively, benefit from increased sperm competition intensity &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/725057&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Kustra et al. 2023  &lt;em&gt;Am. Nat.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. I conducted follow up fertilization experiments to see how female reproductive fluids influence the timing of fertilization and selection on male sneaking delays. This work is still in progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most recently, I published (a quick guide (mini review) on male alternative reproductive tactics&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cell.com/current-biology/abstract/S0960-9822%2825%2900734-1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Kustra and Alonzo 2025  &lt;em&gt;Curr. Biol.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. I have also published a review on the evolution of sperm traits in species with alternative reproductive tactics &lt;a href=&#34;https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rstb.2020.0075&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Kustra and Alonzo 2020 &lt;em&gt;Philos. Trans. R. Soc. B.&lt;/em&gt; )&lt;/a&gt;. We specifically reviewed theoretical predictions on how male alternative reproductive tactics should differ in sperm quality. Despite general expectations that sneaker males should have higher sperm quality, existing theory does not make explicit predictions on how males adopting ARTs should differ in sperm traits. When we look at empirical studies, the majority of studies find no significant difference in sperm performance traits between dominant and sneaker males.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cryptic female choice can maintain reproductive isolation</title>
      <link>https://kustra-matt.github.io/publication/kustra-servedio-alonzo-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kustra-matt.github.io/publication/kustra-servedio-alonzo-2025/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eco-evolutionary dynamics of microbial manipulation</title>
      <link>https://kustra-matt.github.io/project/endo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kustra-matt.github.io/project/endo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been collaborating with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Tyler-Carrier&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tyler Carrier&lt;/a&gt; on developing theory to understand the ecological and evolutionary consequences of reproductive manipulating endosymbionts in marine invertebrates. In our first paper, we show that sex ratio distorting microbes can rapidly spread in broadcast spawners despite causing sperm limitation. Infection in marine invertebrates that produce many small eggs (planktotrophy) results in reduced zygote production. However, infection in marine invertebrates that produce large eggs (lecithotrophy) results in increased zygote production &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/720282&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Kustra and Carrier 2022 &lt;em&gt;Am. Nat.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a follow up paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.asm.org/doi/10.1128/mbio.03655-24&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Kustra and Carrier 2025 &lt;em&gt;mBio&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;, we demonstrate that sex ratio distorting microbes create a sperm limited environment. Under a broad range of ecological conditions, this sperm limited environment results in the rapid evolution of larger eggs. We also identify several candidate species that fit the framework of microbe-induced evolutionary transitions from planktotrophy to lecithotrophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, we are exploring sperm-egg coevolutionary dynamics in broadcast spawners infected with microbial manipulators.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick Guide: Male alternative reproductive tactics</title>
      <link>https://kustra-matt.github.io/publication/kustra-alonzo-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kustra-matt.github.io/publication/kustra-alonzo-2025/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microbes as manipulators of egg size and developmental evolution</title>
      <link>https://kustra-matt.github.io/publication/kustra-carrier-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kustra-matt.github.io/publication/kustra-carrier-2025/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cryptic female choice theory</title>
      <link>https://kustra-matt.github.io/project/cfc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kustra-matt.github.io/project/cfc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In contrast to sexual selection on traits that affect interactions between the sexes before mating, little theoretical research has focused on the coevolution of postmating traits via cryptic female choice (when females bias fertilization toward specific males). I am interested in using theoretical models to understand how cryptic female choice and sperm competition work together to shape the evolution of both male and female reproductive traits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/evlett/article/7/4/191/7191679&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kustra and Alonzo 2023 &lt;em&gt;Evol. Lett.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, we found that incorporating cryptic female choice can result in males investing much less in their ejaculates than predicted by models with sperm competition only. We also found that cryptic female choice resulted in the evolution of genetic correlations between cryptic female choice and sperm traits, even when the strength of cryptic female choice was weak, and the risk of sperm competition was low. This suggests that cryptic female choice may be important even in systems with low multiple mating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a follow up paper (&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/evolut/advance-article/doi/10.1093/evolut/qpaf156/8217261&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kustra et al. 2025 &lt;em&gt;Evolution&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), we tested how cryptic female choice might contribute to speciation. We found that cryptic female choice alone can maintain reproductive isolation under limited but realistic conditions, specifically when the migration rate is low, cryptic preferences are strong, and multiple mating is intermediate. In combination with ecological divergence, cryptic female choice was able to maintain reproductive isolation even at high rates of migration. We also found that conspecific sperm precedence could evolve through reinforcement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am currently working on theory that looks at the evolution of polyandry in hybrid zones and testing how mating preferences interact with cryptic female choice preferences during secondary contact.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The coevolutionary dynamics of cryptic female choice</title>
      <link>https://kustra-matt.github.io/publication/kustra-alonzo-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kustra-matt.github.io/publication/kustra-alonzo-2023/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the spread of microbes that manipulate reproduction in marine invertebrates</title>
      <link>https://kustra-matt.github.io/publication/kustra-carrier-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kustra-matt.github.io/publication/kustra-carrier-2022/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sperm and alternative reproductive tactics: a review of existing theory and empirical data</title>
      <link>https://kustra-matt.github.io/publication/kustra-alonzo-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kustra-matt.github.io/publication/kustra-alonzo-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
