<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Alternative reproductive tactics | Matt Kustra</title>
    <link>https://kustra-matt.github.io/tag/alternative-reproductive-tactics/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://kustra-matt.github.io/tag/alternative-reproductive-tactics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Alternative reproductive tactics</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://kustra-matt.github.io/media/icon_hu968023516251523fc9a78b9c44e7eeb6_483323_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Alternative reproductive tactics</title>
      <link>https://kustra-matt.github.io/tag/alternative-reproductive-tactics/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sexual selection in a changing climate</title>
      <link>https://kustra-matt.github.io/project/climate/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kustra-matt.github.io/project/climate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Reproduction is often more thermally sensitive than survival. Thus, understanding the thermal sensitivity of reproductive interactions is crucial given global warming. Previous studies have almost exclusively focused on interactions before mating, even though important interactions between the sexes also occur after mating (e.g., gamete interactions). Thus, it is unknown how temperature influences female control over fertilization after mating (i.e., cryptic female choice).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a Mediterranean fish (&lt;em&gt;Symphodus ocellatus&lt;/em&gt;), I conducted one of the first experiments to examine how temperature influences postmating female-male interactions &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2025.04.10.648287v1.full&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Kustra et al. &lt;em&gt;Under Review&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. We tested how temperatures relevant to current conditions and climate change projections influence the mechanisms underlying cryptic female choice. Under typical thermal conditions, female reproductive fluid enhances sperm velocity and biases fertilization dynamics to favor high-quality, dominant males over low-quality sneaker males. We find that warmer temperatures decrease female influence on sperm velocity, especially for dominant males. This results in dominant males having slower sperm than sneaker males at warmer temperatures, reducing the expected paternity of high-quality, dominant males. Our results highlight that considering the thermal sensitivity of female-male interactions that occur after mating will be essential for understanding how climate change will influence fertility, reproduction, and sexual selection.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alternative reproductive tactics</title>
      <link>https://kustra-matt.github.io/project/art/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kustra-matt.github.io/project/art/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am interested in the evolution and maintenance of alternative reproductive tactics. My main study system for my PhD was the unique and intriguing ocellated wrasse (&lt;em&gt;Symphodus ocellatus&lt;/em&gt;)! In this species there are three distinct male morphs: (1) nesting males, (2) satellite males, and (3) sneaker males. Females have a strong preference for nesting males who provide all the parental care. Sneaker males will try to sneak in during matings. Satellite males help nesting males chase away sneakers, but when given the opportunity will also try to sneak spawns. During my dissertation, I investigated how sneakers and satellite males differ in sneaking delays and how the social environment influence sneaking delays. We found that satellites have shorter sneak-spawning delays than sneakers, a benefit of their cooperation with nesting males. Sneak-spawning delays decreased with increasing nest activity for sneakers but not for satellites, suggesting that sneakers may, counter intuitively, benefit from increased sperm competition intensity &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/725057&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Kustra et al. 2023  &lt;em&gt;Am. Nat.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. I conducted follow up fertilization experiments to see how female reproductive fluids influence the timing of fertilization and selection on male sneaking delays. This work is still in progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most recently, I published a quick guide (mini review) on male alternative reproductive tactics&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cell.com/current-biology/abstract/S0960-9822%2825%2900734-1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Kustra and Alonzo 2025  &lt;em&gt;Curr. Biol.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. I have also published a review on the evolution of sperm traits in species with alternative reproductive tactics &lt;a href=&#34;https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rstb.2020.0075&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Kustra and Alonzo 2020 &lt;em&gt;Philos. Trans. R. Soc. B.&lt;/em&gt; )&lt;/a&gt;. We specifically reviewed theoretical predictions on how male alternative reproductive tactics should differ in sperm quality. Despite general expectations that sneaker males should have higher sperm quality, existing theory does not make explicit predictions on how males adopting ARTs should differ in sperm traits. When we look at empirical studies, the majority of studies find no significant difference in sperm performance traits between dominant and sneaker males.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick Guide: Male alternative reproductive tactics</title>
      <link>https://kustra-matt.github.io/publication/kustra-alonzo-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kustra-matt.github.io/publication/kustra-alonzo-2025/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sperm and alternative reproductive tactics: a review of existing theory and empirical data</title>
      <link>https://kustra-matt.github.io/publication/kustra-alonzo-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kustra-matt.github.io/publication/kustra-alonzo-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
